<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Long parvula]</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1482</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12869</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23163.13</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100706</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836536</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836536</idno>
            <idno type="VID">816</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12869)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 816)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 12:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>[Long parvula]</title>
                  <author>Stanbridge, John, 1463-1510, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4+] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Theodoric Rood,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1482?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Wrongly attributed to John Stanbridge.</note>
                  <note>Title and imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; consists of leaf B2 and one unsigned leaf only.</note>
                  <note>Leaf B2r, line 1, reads: case As I must goo to the mayster Oporet me ire. Unsigned leaf, recto, line 1 reads: Also when y haue an englysche to be made by thys v[er]bo.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 15294.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 15294 on UMI microfilm reel 12.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Latin language --  Grammar --  Early works to 1500.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:816:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 43 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:816:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 43 -->
            <p>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                  <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>caſe As I muſte goo to the mayſter Oportet me ire ad preceptorem. Good ſcolars haue a pleſure to lerne. Bonos ſcolaſtioos iuuat diſcere. nott wythe ſtondynge ſum tymys they be verbys parſonallys and haue nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natiffe caſys before them Exemplum hic abus delectat me. hec res latet me. Vnde verſus.
<q xml:lang="lat">
                  <l>Quarto iunge iuuat decet ac delectat oportet</l>
                  <l>Et latet illo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abrum"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>rum</ex>
                     </expan> nu new vuit aſſociari</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>C<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>xs .iij. verbys imparſonallys. Refert intereſt &amp; eſt ſe<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t for ꝑ<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inet wyll be conſtruyde wythe a genytiffe caſe of nownys and a ablatiff caſe of .v. ꝓnownys As mea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tua ſua noſtra and veſtra. As in thys Exampull hytt ys for my profytt. Mea intereſt. Hytt ys for thy ꝓfyt Tua in <gap reason="illegible: damage" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap>reſt. Hytt ys for hys profytt. Sua intereſt. Alſo thys verbe Intereſt after precyane ys conſtruyd wythe a ablatiffe caſe off the feminyne gendyr off thys nowne poſſeſſyue Cuius cuia cuiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Vnde verſus.
<q>
                  <l>Refert inter et eſt genitum pro pertinet adde</l>
                  <l>E<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſextum proprie donant pronomina quin<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>
                  </l>
                  <l>N<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> refert noſtra me tu ſu qu o<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> veſtra</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>The verbys imꝑſonallys in the verſys folowynge wyll be conſtruyde wythe a datiff caſe Exem<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we may not ette fleſche on the frydays Non licet nobis commedere carnes in ſextis ferijs. Vnde verſus.</p>
            <q xml:lang="lat">
               <l>Hec libet at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> licet placet et liquet acridit inde</l>
               <l>Congruit euenit et contingit et expedit iſta</l>
               <l>Conuenit incumbit vacat et cedit quo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> preſtat</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:816:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 44 -->
Cuni reliquis paribus ſunt conſotiala datiuis</l>
            </q>
            <p>Pertinet ys conſtruyd wythe an accuſatyff caſe wythe a <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>poſicyon and not wythe a datyff caſe. vt dicendu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ec res ꝑtinet ad me. et non michi. Vnde verſus.
<q xml:lang="lat">Quarto non terno coniunges pertinet apte</q>
            </p>
            <p>All the verbys imꝑſonallys of the paſſyne voyce wylbe conſtruyde wythe a datyff caſe or ellys wythe a ablatyff caſe wythe a prepoſicyon expreſſyd or vnderſtond Exem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>plu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I am pleſyd Michi placetur. The mayſter ys goon Itur a preceptore Hyt nede not att all tymys to ex<g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>ſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe the ablatyffe caſe Exemplum they be goon. itur. they fyȝthythe. pugnatur. what doyth they. quid agitur. they ſyttythe. ſedetur. Vnde verſus.
<q xml:lang="lat">
                  <l>Paſſiue vocis imperſonale datiuis</l>
                  <l>Aut ſextis iungas cum prepoſito preeunte</l>
                  <l>A pueris itur a preceptore venitur</l>
                  <l>Regi ſeruitur ſed non ſibi credo placetur</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Suche verbys as be tokenythe bodyly menynge as Eo is &amp; Venio is may haue often tymys the ſygnyficacyon of the paſſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f voyce in the <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>ter<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fytens &amp; in all the tenſys that be formyd of hym Exemplu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> My mayſter ys cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me mgr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> meꝰ venit<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> my felowys be gon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſocij mei abieru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. when the englyſche of the infenytyf mode cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mythe after any of thys nownys Hora tempꝰ cauſa or locꝰ hyt may be put in a gerundyf in di as hyt ys tyme to pray Tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pus eſt orandi I haue a cauſe to wepe Habeo cauſam flendi. hyt ys vſyd alſo after many adyectyuys and voy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
               <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:816:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 44 -->Alſo when y haue an englyſche to be made by thys v<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> nubo is that that doythe the dede of the verbe ſchalbe put in the datyffe caſe &amp; that that ſufferythe ſchalbe put in the noi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>atyf caſe As in thys exampu<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l My brother ſhall wedde thy ſyſter Fratri meo nubet ſoror tua.</p>
            <p>when y haue a ꝓpyr name of a place towne or cite &amp; yff hyt be the fyrſte declynſone or the ſecounde &amp; the <gap reason="illegible" extent="2+ letters">
                  <desc>••…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>glar numbyr &amp; betokenythe at a place hyt ſchalb<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> pu<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e in a genytyff caſe aduerbyally Exemplu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I goo to g<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer att oxforde Incu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bo gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>matice exonij I was bor<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e at yorke Natꝰ ſum eboraci But &amp; the ꝓpyr name of the place ſygnyfyynge att a place by the plurell numbyr or ellys any other declynſone ſaue the fyrſte declynſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne or the ſecounde hyt ſchalbe put in the ablatyf caſe aduerby<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ally wythe owte a <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>poſicyon as y haue a brother at ſcho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le at attenys Eſt michi frater ſtud<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ns athenis A<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſo to a place yff hyt be a ꝓpyr name of a place hyt ſch<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lbe put in the accuſatyff caſe wythe owte a <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>p<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſicyon what ſum euer declynſone or numbyr that hyt be not wythe ſton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge ſum tymys y may put a prepoſicyon b<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fore hym As y go to oxforde eo oxoniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vel ad o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I ſchall go to london Ibo londi<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vel ad lond<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Alſo fro a place and yff hyt be a ꝓpyr name of a place ys the ſyne of the ablatyff caſe wythe owte a <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>poſicyon what ſum euer de clynſone or numbyr hyt be As y cum fro london Venio londind I cum fro oxford Venio oxonio not wythe ſton<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dynge ſum tymys y may take a <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>poſycyon by fore hym
<pb facs="tcp:816:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 45 -->
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f venio ab oxonio. venio a londino.</p>
            <p>Theys rulys off propyr names be to be vnderſtonde off ſyche that byne not compownde for and they be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pownde euer more y muſte putte a prepoſycyone before them As y haue byn at ſeynte Iamys Fui apud ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum iacobum I goo to ſaynte Iamys Vado ad ſanctum iacobum I come fro ſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yntt Iemys Veni a ſancto iaco<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bo. Alſo thys .iiij. nownys Rus Domus Humus belli and Milicia fol<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>w the the rulys of ꝓpyr names of pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces. as y haue be att home Fui domi I goo home Vado domu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I cum fro home Venio a domo. Not wythe ſton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge Rus ys putte of tener adu<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:aber"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>er</ex>
               </expan>byally in the datyf caſe then in the ablatyff Exemplu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I haue be in the contrey. ruri fui. My fadyr dwellythe in the contrey. pater meus ruri habitat.</p>
            <p>Thys nowne domus ys thus declynyde Nominatiuo hec domus genitiuo huius domi vel domus datiuo huic do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mui accuſatiuo hanc domu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vocatiuo o domus ablatiuo ab hac domo Et plu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> noi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>atiuo he domꝰ genitiuo ha<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abrum"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>rum</ex>
               </expan> domo<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abrum"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>rum</ex>
               </expan> vel domuu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> datiuo hijs domibus accuſatiuo has domos vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catiuo o domꝰ ablatiuo ab hijs domibus. Vnde verſus.
<q>
                  <l>Per quartu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> domus eſt flectenda niſi ſextus</l>
                  <l>Singularis quartus pluralis et eſt gemtiuus</l>
                  <l>In numero vtro<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſemper flexus vtriuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>
                  </l>
               </q>
when that y haue a queſtyon aſkyd y ſhall anſwere euer more by the ſame caſe that the queſtyon ys aſchede by ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cepte hytt be aſkyd by a poſſeſſyue Exemplu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> queris</p>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
               <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:816:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 45 -->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
